This is Crazy Thursday, buy one get one free
这个是疯狂星期4V我50
Hehe
呵呵呃
Actually, I think recording at this moment is pretty great
其实感觉这时候录像是非常好的
In this episode, I'll talk about a very simple example
我这期讲一个讲一个非常简单的例子
I really don't understand this kind of behavior from parents in Haidian.
就是我非常不理解海淀家长的这种
This tiger parenting approach.
鸡娃的行为啊
I think tiger parenting is a last resort.
鸡娃的行为我认为是人实在没有招了啊
When they realize they can't push themselves, they start pushing their kids.
在激自己发现不行的情况下去激娃啊
Generally speaking, I feel that by coming to Haidian District,
通常来讲也觉得就是我来到了海淀区
I've gained access to such a high-level educational environment.
我取得了这么高级的这种教育资源的环境
Why wouldn't my child study hard?
孩子为什么就不好好学习呢
But the resources and environment are one thing,
但其实资源环境是一回事
What matters most is what kind of seed this is.
重要的是这个东西到底是什么种子啊
As a medical student,
你作为一个学医代啊
you have achieved very high academic performance.
你取得了非常高的学习成绩
Logically, the second generation should achieve even higher grades,
按理说第二代取得比你更高的成绩的
but the probability of that is not high.
这个概率呢并不高
Considering you are the pinnacle of intelligence in your family,
因为你作为你家庭的智慧的一个巅
from a genetic perspective, the next generation tends to regress to the mean. So, the likelihood of your offspring having outstanding academic performance is not high. And to be honest when it comes to my friends around me
峰的遗传的一个现象来讲的话 下一代就会均值回归啊 所以你的后代学习成绩非常好的 可能性呢并不高 而且说实在的 我很多的时候我身边这些朋友来讲
they often wonder how to properly raise their children
他们的孩子啊到底应该怎样培养
they really don’t know
他是不知道的
the cultivation of some key skills
一些关键能力的培养呢
doesn’t take up much of her time
她花的时间呢并不多
You're like my sister, taking the kids to learn taekwondo.
你像我的妹妹是她带孩子去学跆拳道啊
to learn English
去学英语啊
to learn math
去学数学啊
Going to learn an instrument
去学乐器
I think it's all useless
我觉得都是没有用的
Because if the child doesn't love learning
因为孩子本身不爱学习的话
taking them to practice this
你去带他去练习这个啊
or sports activities
体育方面的东西
or artistic activities
还是艺术方面的东西
or cultural activities
还是文化方面的东西
is actually not effective
其实是没有用的
the most important thing is that the child is interested in something
最重要的是孩子自己对某些东西东西感兴趣
And I think a child
而我觉得一个几岁的孩子啊
around six to nine years old
6789岁
won't show their specific talents before the age of ten
十岁以前是不会凸显自己的专职方面的才能
a person truly reveals their talents around fourteen or fifteen
一个人真正显现自己才能的时候是十四五岁
sixteen or seventeen
十六七岁
eighteen or nineteen
十八九岁的时候啊
even then, it might still be a bit early
甚至这时候还有点早啊
I've always been telling everyone
我一直跟大家说
this is about English education
这个是英语教育
It shouldn't be done before the age of 12.
不应该在12岁之前进行
Because before the age of 12,
因为12岁之前
you don't have a good grasp of cultural elements, especially the Chinese language environment, subject-verb- subject-verb-object, and things like attributive, adverbial, and complement are not fully understood by you. So, you need to have a good understanding of your modern language.
你对于这种啊文化上面的东西 特别是中文的语文的环境 主谓丁呃 主谓宾 定状补这些东西你都不太了解到底是什么东西 所以你需要对自己的现代的语言有所了解啊
I think the reason many people struggle in a short period of time is
我觉得很多人之所以在一个很短的一个
It's quite simple, from a very early age, there was a focus on nurturing the child.
很简单的一个啊很早期就对孩子有一种培养的
The fundamental reason
根本的原因
lies in their exposure to so many geniuses.
就在于他们见识了太多的天才
Geniuses.
天才
A child's song drifted to Sanya.
小孩歌漂流到三亚
A child ran 5 kilometers.
小孩歌横跑5km
From Anhui to Henan.
从安徽跑到河南
Such things, how can they be described?
这种事情都是一种怎么说呢
It's like the memories from a past life haven't been erased.
上辈子的记忆没清理干净
The outcome is that many talents are required for such things.
导致的结果可是这类的很多的才能来讲
Let's talk about the saying 'great things come to those who wait'.
咱们讲大器免成
Great things come to those who wait.
大器晚成
Many things, you see,
很多事情啊
are truly useful to society,
真是到对社会上有用的东西
these talents might not emerge until you're in your twenties,
这才能甚至是在你20岁
or even your thirties.
30岁才能得到的一些技能
So you can't be too hasty.
所以你不能太着急
Therefore, pushing kids too hard has no benefits.
所以鸡娃没有任何好处
The most important thing for a child is to be happy.
因为孩子最重要的是要快乐
It’s about the accumulation of positive experiences during childhood.
要他对童年的这种积累啊
This will influence his memories of childhood many years later. When he looks back, he should have fond memories of his childhood. So, when it comes to a child’s development, it’s crucial to focus on cultivating good behavior and habits. In this area, I recommend a balanced approach.
导致他以后的多少多少年以后 回想起童年的时候是一种快乐的回忆 所以你需要对孩子来讲的培养啊 是一个是他的行为习惯的培养啊 当然这个方面我啊比较建议正常
For example, when it comes to my own experience,
比如说像我这个怎么说呢
many children around me have regular routines for meals and sleep.
我周围的孩子很多人都是啊吃饭睡觉定点儿啊
Attend school regularly
正常上学
Maintain a regular schedule
正常作息
Engage in regular exercise
正常运动啊
Keep yourself in good health
把身体弄得好好的
This is the right approach
这个东西是正确的
But when it comes to skill development
但是从技能上的培养来讲
You just need to ensure the child can survive
你只要让孩子能活下去啊
That's really all it takes
其实就可以了
Many parents are too anxious
很多家长太着急
You, like me when I was a kid,
你像我小时候来讲
also practiced the electronic keyboard,
也练过电子琴
also took vocal lessons,
也练过声乐
also dabbled in computers,
也练过什么计算机
also tried various input methods,
也练过各种各样的输入法
also played Go,
也练过围棋
also practiced calligraphy,
也练过这个书法
but what's the point of all these things?
可是这种东西到底有什么用呢
and even took art classes.
还练过美术呢
Actually, I find these things to be the worst.
我实际上这些东西是最差的
I've always disliked these things
我一直不喜欢这些东西
I'm also not willing to spend more time learning about them.
我也不愿意花更多的时间去学习这方面的东西
So, when it comes to it,
所以来讲的话
this kind of accumulation is completely useless to me.
这方面的东西这种积累对我来讲一点用都没有
Over time, it can even create a rebellious attitude.
时间长了以后反而会让形成一种逆反心理
My art has always been graded on a two-point scale
我的美术一直是按两分
I have a particular disinterest in things like art and calligraphy. So, to be honest, parents in Haidian District say, Why am I particularly reluctant to go out for meals? Because every time it's mealtime, I notice parents picking up their kids right after school,
我对美术书法之类的东西都特别的不感兴趣 所以海淀区的家长说实在的 我为什么特别不愿意出去吃饭啊 因为一到饭点的时候 就发现这个家长啊接了这个刚放学的孩子
and then start scolding them right away,
然后就过来就对孩子各种训斥啊
Why didn’t you do your homework?
你作业为什么没写啊
Why are your grades so poor?
成绩为什么不好啊
Why do you always play on the tablet when you get home?
为什么天天回家玩平板啊
It’s always the same story.
全都是这样
And yet, these parents themselves don’t earn much either.
然后呢家长呢自己呢挣不了几个臭子儿啊
Then, you also need to scold the child in various aspects.
然后呢还要对孩子进行各方面的训斥啊
Parents are already very tired.
家长自己已经很累了
So, I suggest you,
所以我就建议你
if you are normal,
如果你要是正常的话啊
if you think your child is just an average person,
你要觉得你孩子就是一个平庸的人的话
don't focus on his development before the age of 12.
你不要在12岁之前对他重点培养啊
What I believe truly deserves cultivation is,
所谓的培养我觉得真正应该值得培养的
for example, which good school he can get into for college,
比如说你为他高考能上哪个好学校啊
you should start preparing in advance.
你提前培养
No matter if you choose the selection route
不管你是选调啊
or the unconventional path through the college entrance exam or the arts exam route
还是说非正常的走高考路线还是走艺考路线
This is what I can see
这是我能够看见的啊
Of course, not everyone is suited for the arts exam route
当然不是说所有人都适合走艺考路线
But I’ve always told everyone
但我一直跟大家说
The arts exam route is a relatively easier one
艺考路线是一个比较简单的
to boost your college entrance exam performance
获得这个高考呢能够提升一个水平啊
You could get into a first-tier university
你上一本
But you could get into a 211 university You can get into a 211 university but you could also aim for a 985 Often, the arts exams can increase your chances of getting into a prestigious university This is a good thing And the arts are relatively easier
但是你能上211 你考得上211 但能上985啊 很多的时候通过艺考的方式增加来讲 你这个进入名校的概率 这是件好事 而且艺术这东西呢比较水
They can reduce the difficulty of your middle and high school studies
它能降低你这个初高中学习的那个难度
You need to understand
你一定要明白
that your child’s IQ is on the lower side
自己的孩子在智商的水平上来讲是比较低的
In terms of your asset allocation,
而你在资产上的配置上来讲的话
your level is relatively low.
你的水平是比较低的
So, for an ordinary family,
所以鸡孩子是已经是一个普通家庭以后
this is the least desirable option.
最没有办法的一种办法了
A typical person,
一个正常的一个人啊
when they enter their youth,
进入年轻的时代
in their twenties and thirties,
进入二三十岁
or even in their forties and fifties,
四十五十岁的那年代的话
should find ways to increase the value of their assets.
他应该想办法让自己的资产升值啊
Double your career
让自己的事业翻番
This time, he should focus on
这次他应该干的事情
Of course
当然来讲
You're taking your family
你带着家庭啊
Starting a business with debt
带着负债去创业啊
Trying to do something
去搞什么东西
That sounds a bit like a fairy tale
这有点天方夜谭了啊
I don't think so
我也不觉得
One person can't entirely rely on these things
一个人能够完完全全的通过这些东西
having a family
又有拥有家庭
and a career
又拥有事业
is not very likely
不太可能
I think one has to make sacrifices
我觉得人一定会有牺牲的
like I sacrificed my marriage
你要像我牺牲了婚姻
so having a career is a common human desire
所以有了事业这个东西才是一个人之常情
a normal state of affairs because if you want to achieve something great the most important thing isn't actually the funding It's a complete cycle of your experiences. You need to have a complete one. Something that allows you to unleash your energy in Space
一个正常的一个状态 因为你要想搞一番事业 最重要的其实主要是不是资金 而是你一个完完整整的一个经历的一个循环啊 你需要有一个完整的一个 能够施展你的精力空间的一个东西
And this thing should be something you find within your lifetime.
而且这个东西还是得在你在有生之年
Finding the right track for yourself.
找到了自己合适的赛道
This is incredibly important.
这个东西太重要了啊
So we say that pushing your kids is the last resort.
所以我们说说鸡娃是最后一种没有办法的选择
What you should really accumulate is your initial capital.
你真正应该积累的是你的原始资本
If you accumulate initial capital,
如果你积累了原始资本
you might end up not getting married,
你有可能就走向不结婚
or not having children.
有可能走向不生孩子那种状态
So, to put it another way,
所以来讲
you should make a bold move in your career,
你去对事业进行一次冲击
make a second attempt,
两次冲击
or even a third attempt, with small-scale trials and errors.
三次冲击进行小范围试错的话
You might actually see your career take off.
其实你本身有可能事业起飞了
And these issues would be resolved.
你这些问题也就解决了
What we usually see is,
所以我们通常看到的是
more people pin their hopes on the next generation.
更多的人呢寄希望于下一代
I think those who truly pin their hopes on the next generation,
我觉得真正寄希望于下一代的人
are actually at a loss with their own generation.
实在是对自己这一代是没有办法了
So I really think parents in Haidian District,
所以我真的觉得海淀区的家长
you can relax a bit,
你们可以放松一点
and have a second spring in your careers,
可以在事业上搞上第二春
rather than burdening your children,
而不是要麻烦自己的孩子
because your children might, in terms of ability, be even less capable than you at the genetic level.
因为你的孩子有可能能力上 反而在基因的水平上来讲还不如你